Capital District Regional Planning Commission; Records apap380
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Capital District Regional Planning Commission Records
1934-2013
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Capital District Regional Planning Commission
apap380
55.07 cubic ft.
This collection documents the comprehensive planning work of New York's Capital District Regional Planning Commission across several decades.
Content Description
The collection contains plans; proposals; maps; reports; studies; booklets on codes, regulations, and zoning laws; and correspondence. The materials discuss plans for cities and counties in New York's Capital Region as well as the Adirondacks.
Biographical Note
The Capital District Regional Planning Commission (CDRPC) is a regional planning and resource center, established pursuant to New York State law, serving Albany, Rensselaer, Saratoga, and Schenectady counties. CDRPC was created in 1967 by a cooperative agreement amongst these four counties. Its original purpose was to perform and support comprehensive planning work, including surveys, planning services, technical services, and the formulation of plans and policies to promote coordinated development of the entire Capital Region. Over time, the mission of the CDRPC evolved in response to changes in the needs of the Capital Region, funding sources, organizational structures, and information technology. While continuing to provide a wide variety of comprehensive planning services, CDRPC has also assumed the functions of Data and Information Center, Economic Development District, Foreign-Trade Zone Administrator, Climate Smart Communities Coordinator, and Water Quality Manager.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged into six series: Albany County, Rensselaer County, Saratoga County, Schenectady County, Capital District, and Greater Region. Planning documents that describe work sited in only one of the four home counties of the Capital District are filed in the series named for that county, labeled with the most relevant village, town, or city. For documents that include plans that span county boundaries within the Capital District -- e.g., the Port of Albany or the I-87 Northway -- those have been filed in the series entitled "Capital District." All other documents in the series, whose plans pertain to areas entirely outside the four home counties of the Capital District, are filed in the series entitled "Greater Region." Examples of the last category include plans for the Adirondack Park, the Lower Hudson River, and western New York. Some common file types within the collection include comprehensive/master plans, local waterfront revitalization plans, environmental impact assessments, soil surveys, and water/sewer plans. A special indication is present for those documents that contain either a supplemental or a fold-out map. Particular sites for which there are a substantial number of documents include the Albany Pine Bush Preserve, the Port of Albany, Albany Airport, and Adirondack Park. The earliest dated documents in the collection are USGS soil surveys from the 1930s. However, the great majority of documents date from the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Mark A. Castiglione, executive director, Capital District Regional Planning Commission, donated all materials in this collection to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in July 2019.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Capital District Regional Planning Commission; Albany, New York; Rensselaer County, New York; Schenectady, New York; Regional planning--New York (State)
- Albany County, 1942-2013; 1; 11.42 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains files pertaining to planning decisions in Albany County, New York. There are a wide variety of documents covering county-level planning -- e.g., open space plans, county land use regulations, transportation plans for I-87/Northway, as well as plans involving the airport and the Pine Bush Preserve. There are also plans for specific municipalities within the county: villages, towns, and the City of Albany, itself. For the City of Albany, there are housing studies, community buying guides, economic development strategies, community improvement program reports, land use inventories, downtown development plans, to name a few of the most common document types.
  - [City of] Albany, Air Quality in the City of Albany, Environmental Assessment Program, 1975 October (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany Ahead: An Historic City's Bright Future, 1985 February (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany, Area Chamber of Commerce 1978-1979 Membership Directory/Buyers Guide, Section Two (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany: City in Rebirth, 1979 March (Box 1, Folder 4)
    General
    Supplemental Map Included
  - [City of] Albany, Albany Heritage, Fall Program, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany Housing Authorities Noise Study for Thatcher Homes, Final Report, 1978 March (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany Housing Authority Urban Initiatives (1 of 2), 1978 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany Housing Authority Urban Initiatives (2 of 2), 1978 August (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany, New York, Capital City for Business [Promotional Material From Capital City Renaissance Corp.], Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany, New York's Community Buying Guide: Arbor Hill, 1977 June (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany, New York's Community Buying Guide: Central Avenue Business District, 1977 June (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany New York's Community Buying Guide: South End, 1977 July (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany New York's Community Buying Guide: West Hill, 1977 July (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany Parking Authority Garage no. 2, Final Environment Impact Statement, 1986 June (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany Topics Signal System Study, [NYS DOT], 1971 December (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany: Transit Supportive Development [Case Study], 2008 September-2008 December (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany's Children: Albany's Future, A Report of the Strategic Planning Committee of the Albany School District, 1989 November (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - [City of] Albany, Albany's Children: Albany's Future, A Strategic Plan for the Albany City School District, 1990 January (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - [City of] Albany, Animal Habitats in the City of Albany, 1976 November (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - [City of] Albany, Answers: Albany, New York Solid Waste Energy Recovery System Data, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - [City of] Albany, Answers: Albany, New York Solid Waste Energy Recovery System, Preliminary Engineering Report, 1975 October (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - [City of] Albany, Application for Workable Program Certification or Re-Certification [US Dept. of HUD] (1 of 2), 1972 April (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - [City of] Albany, Application for Workable Program Certification or Re-Certification [US Dept. of HUD] (2 of 2), 1972 April (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - [City of] Albany, Brief Description of Properties Censused, 1975 August (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - [City of] Albany, Business Opportunities and Employment, 1985 February (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - [City of] Albany, Capital Cities of the Fifty States, 1990 November (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - [City of] Albany, Capitalize Albany: Economic Development Strategy for New York's Capital City, 1996 February (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - [City of] Albany, Capitalize Albany: Economic Development Strategy for New York's Capital City, [Color Booklet], Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - [City of] Albany, Case Study: Rexford Pump and Supply Co., Inc., 1982 March (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - [City of] Albany, Civil Service Rules, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - [City of] Albany, Commercial Revitalization Strategy Central Avenue, 1980 March (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - [City of] Albany, Community Development Program, Program Information, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - [City of] Albany, Community Development Project, Program Status Report, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - [City of] Albany, Community Improvement Program [Brochure], Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - [City of] Albany, Community Improvement Program, The Economic Basis for Renewal, Albany, New York, Interim Report (1 of 2), 1968 March (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - [City of] Albany, Community Improvement Program, The Economic Basis for Renewal, Albany, New York, Interim Report (2 of 2), 1968 March (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - [City of] Albany, Community Improvement Program, Improvement Action Program [Summary Report], 1968 December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - [City of] Albany, Community Improvement Program Report on Physical Conditions and Recommendations for Treatment [Interim Report], 1968 November (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - [City of] Albany, Community Profile, Albany, New York, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - [City of] Albany, Community Residence Inventory, 1990 March (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - [City of] Albany, Comprehensive Housing Affordability Strategy (CHAS), [Draft], 1993 October (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - [City of] Albany, Computer Park at the Pines, Draft Environmental Impact Statement, 1985 June (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - [City of] Albany, Computer Park at the Pines, Final Environmental Impact Statement, 1985 July (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - [City of] Albany, Computer Park at the Pines, Office Building CP-37, 1988 September (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - [City of] Albany, Consolidated Request for Proposals, Department of Housing and Community Development, 1994 December (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - [City of] Albany, A Development Strategy for Downtown Albany, 1973 September (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - [City of] Albany, Downtown Albany Development Plan, [Report Brochure], 1969 April (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - [City of] Albany, Downtown Albany Retail and Office Rents, Vicinity of North Pearl and State Streets, 1982 March (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - [City of] Albany, Downtown Circulation Study, Executive Report, 1978 November (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - [City of] Albany, Downtown Circulation Study, Technical Report, 1978 November (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - [City of] Albany, Economic Base Study of Downtown Albany, 1961 September (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - [City of] Albany, Economic Development in the City of Albany, Coordination of Business and Public Development Activities, [Workshop Program], 1977 December (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - [City of] Albany, Economic Development Strategies [Memo], 1973 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - [City of] Albany, An Economic Development Strategy Downtown Albany, 1973 September (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - [City of] Albany, Environmental Assessment Program, Summary of Soil Conditions, Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - [City of] Albany, Environmental Assessment Program Summary of Soil Conditions [Report], 1975 September (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - [City of] Albany, Environmental Developmental Factors, 1976 June (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - [City of] Albany, Evaluation of Recreation Program Participation and Distribution of Properties and Facilities by Census Tract…, 1976 August (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - [City of] Albany, Existing Land Use Inventory, Purpose and Methodology [Technical Memorandum], 1976 May (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - [City of] Albany, Fact Finders 1986 Rental Housing Survey, 1986 August (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - [City of] Albany, Feeling at Home in Albany, Undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - [City of] Albany, Final Environmental Impact Statement, Karner Meadows Residential Subdivision, 1985 May (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - [City of] Albany, Final Report, Albany Strategic Planning Committee, Downtown, 1985 February (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - [City of] Albany, Final Report, Albany Strategic Planning Committee, Government Finances and Services, 1985 February (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - [City of] Albany, Final Report, Albany Strategic Planning Committee, Housing and Community Development, 1985 March (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - [City of] Albany, Financial Baseline: Albany Wastewater Facility Plan, Federal Grant (EPA/DEC) #C-36-960-01, 1980 September (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - [City of] Albany, General Plan for City of Albany, New York, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - [City of] Albany, Gentrification and Development in the City of Albany, 1981 April (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - [City of] Albany, Guide to the Community Development Block Grant, 1994 November (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - [City of] Albany, Historic Resources Inventory: Five Community Development Areas, 1976 June (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - [City of] Albany, Housing Profile of the City of Albany, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - [City of] Albany, Housing Units Gained Through New Construction and Rehabilitation 1980 to 1989, 1989 December (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - [City of] Albany, The Inner City: A Study of the Community Needs Albany, New York, 1971 December (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - [City of] Albany, Institutional Baseline: Albany Wastewater Facility Plan, Federal Grant (EPA/DEC) #c-36-960-01, 1980 September (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - [City of] Albany, John Boyd Thacher [sic] Homes Tenant Survey, 1978 March (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - [City of] Albany, Land Use in the City of Albany, Background Studies and Concept Plan Alternatives, 1976 June (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - [City of] Albany, Local Waterfront Revitalization Program, 1987 April (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - [City of] Albany, Local Waterfront Revitalization Program, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - [City of] Albany, Market Analysis: Downtown Albany, N.Y., 1982 February (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - [City of] Albany, Master Plan, Report 3: Land Uses, 1958 December (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - [City of] Albany, National Water Systems in the City of Albany, 1976 June (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - [City of] Albany, Neighborhood Conditions Report, Capital Improvement Recommendations for Community Development Treatment Areas, 1976 June (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - [City of] Albany, New Audience Support Facilities as an Element in Downtown Albany Revitalization, Analysis and Conclusions, 1973 October (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - [City of] Albany, A New Town… in Town, Albany Times Union [Newspaper Article], 1974 April (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - [City of] Albany, Noise and the City of Albany, Environmental Analysis Report, 1976 June (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - [City of] Albany, Norstar Plaza Final Environmental Impact Statement (1 of 2), 1984 November (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - [City of] Albany, Norstar Plaza Final Environmental Impact Statement (2 of 2), 1984 November (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - [City of] Albany, The North Albany Report, 1989 December (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - [City of] Albany, Office Space Profile Albany County, City of Albany and Downtown Albany, 1982 March (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - [City of] Albany, Park and Playgrounds [Data from one-week census in August, 1975], Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - [City of] Albany, Partnerships to Progress, Realizing Albany's Future, Evaluating the Implementation of Albany's 1985 Strategic Plan, 1989 January (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - [City of] Albany, Phase 1 Solid Waste Resource Recovery Feasibility Study, Executive Summary, 1983 August (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - [City of] Albany, Phase 1 Solid Waste Resource Recovery Feasibility Analysis, Vol 1 Detailed Report (1 of 2), 1983 July (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - [City of] Albany, Phase 1 Solid Waste Resource Recovery Feasibility Analysis, Vol 1 Detailed Report (2 of 2), 1983 July (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - [City of] Albany, Phase 1 Solid Waste Resource Recovery Feasibility Analysis, Vol 2, Appendix, 1983 July (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - [City of] Albany, Preliminary Report of the Mayor's Advisory Task Force on Homeless Housing, 1991 January (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - [City of] Albany, The Present Condition of Downtown Albany: An Analysis of Past Trends and Future Scenarios, 1984 April (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - [City of] Albany, Public Facilities Inventory and Needs Analysis, Comprehensive Planning Assistance Program, 1976 June (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - [City of] Albany, Public Work: City, County and State [Periodical], 1981 May (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - [City of] Albany, Rapp Road Sanitary Land Fill Expansion, Answer Watershed Recycling Plan, Vol. 3, Appendix S., 1988 August (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - [City of] Albany, Rapp Road Sanitary Landfill Expansion, Minimum Area Requirements for Long-Term Conservation of the Albany Pine Bush…, Vol IV, 1988 August (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - [City of] Albany, Recreation Plan Technical Report, Group Interviews, Continuing Education Classes, 1975 December (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - [City of] Albany, Recreation Plan Technical Report, Group Interviews, High School Students, 1975 November-1975 December (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - [City of] Albany, Report on the Architectural Survey of Community Development Areas 1,2,3,4 and 5, 1976 June (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - [City of] Albany, Report of the Temporary State Commission on the Capital City, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - [City of] Albany, Request for Proposal, Broadway Redevelopment Site, 1987 December (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - [City of] Albany, Research and Program Evaluation Report on the Centralized Emergency Shelter Intake Service (CESIS), 1983 February (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - [City of] Albany, Revitalization Strategies for North Albany, [SUNY MRP Planning Studio], 2000 September-2000 December (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - [City of] Albany, Special Report: Albany Inner City Recreation Plan Committee, 1976 September (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - [City of] Albany, Steamboat Square: From our Point Of View… [Albany Housing Authority Promotional Booklet], Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - [City of] Albany, [Study on Mentally In Homeless in Albany], 1985 June (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - [City of] Albany, Summary Report Special Study for the City of Albany [on Usage of School Buildings], 1976 April (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - [City of] Albany, A Survey of Businesses Located in Albany's Inner City: Funding and Recommendations, 1977 June (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - [City of] Albany, Technical Memorandum No. 2, Analysis of Existing Land Use, Albany Urban Renewal Agency, Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - [City of] Albany, Union Station Adaptive Reuse Study, 1977 May (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - [City of] Albany, Waterfront Revitalization Albany, 1985 March (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - [City of] Albany, Zoning Ordinance [Booklet], 1968 May (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Albany and Schenectady Counties, Soil Survey, Series 1936, No. 16, 1942 May (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Albany County, 701 Preliminary Land Use Program 1976 Inventory of Transportation Systems, Facilities and Plans, 1977 May (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Albany County, 1980 Census of Population Characteristics of People and Housing, Undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Albany County, Airport Layout Plan Report, 1969 December (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Albany County, Albany County Agricultural and Farmland Protection Plan, 2004 May (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Albany County, Albany County Airport Authority, Comprehensive Annual Financial Report Year Ended December 31, 2008, 2009 July (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Albany County, Albany County Airport Authority Comprehensive Annual Financial Report, Year Ended December 31, 2009, 2010 May (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Albany County, Albany County Airport Noise Control and Land Use Compatibility Study, Interim Report #3, 1981 February (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Albany County, Albany County Airport Development Plan, 1963 August (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Albany County, Albany County Airport Noise Control and Land Use Compatibility Study, Interim Report Number 2, 1980 June (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Albany County, Albany County Airport Runway 19 Proposed Extension, Preliminary Environmental Impact Assessment, 1978 September (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Albany County, Albany County Airport Updated Airport Layout Plan and Land Use Study, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Albany County, Albany County at the Crossroads, 1986 June (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Albany County, Albany County Comprehensive Plan 1971-1977 Study Design, 1971 June (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Albany County, Albany County Comprehensive Public Water Supply Study (Preliminary), 1968 May (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Albany County, Albany County Land Development Plan, 1978 April (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Albany County, Albany County Land Use and Development Plan, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Albany County, Albany County Land Use Development Plan, 1978 April (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Albany County, Albany County Land Use and Development Plan, (Final Draft), 1978 April (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Albany County, Albany County New York, Guide to the Region, Undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Albany County, Albany County, N.Y., Housing and Construction Study, 1971 July (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Albany County, Albany County, New York in REM Properties Reuse Strategies, Summary Technical Report, 1980 June (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Albany County, Albany County, New York Industrial Sites Information System, Summary Report SR 701/604, 19680 June (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Albany County, Albany County Overall Economic Development Plan Progress Report, 1980 June (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Albany County, Albany County Planning Board Residential Design Standards and Performance Specifications, 1978 October (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Albany County, Albany County Preliminary Historic Resources Inventory, 1979 June (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Albany County, Albany County Preliminary Land Use Plan, Technical Memorandum LUP-1, 1977 May (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Albany County, Albany County Resource Appraisal of Potential Outdoor Recreation Development, (Advance Copy), 1969 June (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Albany County, Albany County Resources Development Center, Serving the People [Informational Brochure], Undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Albany County, Albany County Senior Housing Study By Center for the Study of Aging, 1982 November (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Albany County, Albany County Soil Conservation District Program, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Albany County, Albany County (West) Comprehensive Sewage Study, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Albany County, Albany County Youth Bureau Census [Technical Report], 1976 April (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Albany County, Albany Crosstown Extension Northside Northway Connection [Unofficial Print Map], Undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Albany County, Albany County New York's Capital Community [Promotional Booklet], Undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Albany County, Albany Northside-Northway Connection, Phase 2 Report, 1972 July (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Albany County, Alternative Reuse Strategies for Concentrations of County Owned Properties, 1980 June (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Albany County, Appraisal of Potential for Outdoor recreational Development and Inventory of Existing Recreation Areas, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Albany County, Assorted Correspondence, Undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Albany County, Census of Voluntary Agency Participants, 1975 December (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Albany County, Corrections Facility Standards Implementation Program for Albany County, New York, 1979 January (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Albany County, County of Albany Comprehensive Youth Service Plan, annual Progress Report, July 1, 1988-June 30, 1989, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Albany County, County of Albany Office of the County Clerk (Pamphlet), Undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Albany County, Draft Feasibility Survey of Waste Disposal Alternatives for Albany Steam Station, 1980 March (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Albany County, Draft Generic Environmental Impact Statement for the Albany Pine Bush, (1 of 2), 1986 February (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Albany County, Draft Generic Environmental Impact Statement for the Albany Pine Bush, (2 of 2), 1986 February (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Albany County, Draft Report on Energy Consumption in Albany County, New York in 1980, Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Albany County, Drive It Yourself Tour of Albany County, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 7)